Greetings, sir.
先生
Some rare guests!
稀客啊
Professor Hu.
胡教授
Are you here to learn English from me?
怎么 你这是来跟我学英文
Or?
还是
Professor Gu, I'm here to seek you as a master.
辜教授 我是来向您拜师的
How interesting!
真新鲜
You speak in the vernacular,
你这讲白话文的
yet come here to learn English poems.
跟我这讲洋诗的学习
It doesn't make any sense.
不搭呀
Sir, I'm sincerely here to learn from you.
先生 今天我真是来向您请教的
In that case, have you brought any presents to your master-to-be?
那带拜师礼了吗
Presents,
拜师礼
didn't you bring them?
你没带吗
Shouchang, have you brought any
守常带了吗
presents to our master-to-be?
拜师礼
I thought it's you who came to be apprenticed.
不是你拜师吗
Right, didn't you bring the presents?
对那你拜师没带吗
Right?
是吧
It's him seeking to be apprenticed.
他拜师
Professor Gu, I'll treat you with a meal.
辜教授 我请您吃饭
I, Gu Hongming, have dined with the emperor before,
我辜鸿铭跟皇上一起用过膳
I also have eaten next to coolies.
跟力巴也吃过饭
But with snobs who forget their origins and toady to foreign powers,
可是跟数典忘祖 崇洋媚外的人
never ever!
从来没有
Not even once!
没有
Mr. Tangsheng, I apologize about the confusion.
汤生先生 您不要误会
We're here by order of Mr. Cai
我们哪是奉蔡先生之命
and we're sending this invitation on behalf of Peking University.
代表北大请您的
By order of Mr. Cai?
蔡先生啊
Exactly.
没错
Then I must honor this invitation.
那这个面子我得给
I must.
我得给
But I also have one condition.
不过我有个条件
Please let us know.
您说
I will pick the restaurant and order drinks and dishes.
饭庄子和酒水菜单得我自己挑
And my two servants will also be there to wait on me.
我这两个仆人呢得跟着伺候着
Would you concur with this condition?
这个条件您能同意吗
We concur, absolutely!
同意 完全同意
It's all up to you to decide.
一切听您安排
Well then, I'll ask my servants to make arrangement.
那好 那我就让他们去准备
You can wait for further notice.
你们就等通知吧
Alright.
好
Sir, please excuse us then.
那先生 我们告辞了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
好谢了
Please come in side.
里边请
Had our guests arrived?
客人来了
Yes, they have.
来了
How many of them?
几位呀
Oh, my goodness, today our Donxing Inn
今儿个我们东兴楼
has an eye-opener!
可算长了见识了
This Master Gu you invited
这位请客的辜老爷啊
has a huge display.
谱摆得太大了
He has two servants waiting on him.
两位仆人伺候着
They are all wearing queues. How dazzling!
一水儿的长子
Brother Zhongfu,
仲甫兄
I feel uncertain now --
我这心里头有点打鼓
What if we didn't bring enough money?
这钱带得不够怎么办
Our guest is probably going to be as extravagant as possible.
这位爷可是怎么邪乎怎么作的主
Not necessarily.
不至于
The reason why he's so affected is
他之所以这么造作
because he didn't want to be slighted.
就是不想让别人冷落他
He simply lacks confidence.
心虚得很
Why don't you turn off the lights in daytime? Such a waste of wax
大白天的大灯就灭了吧费蜡
Professor Gu, wishing you good health. (In Qing Dynasty style)
辜教授 给您请安
We apologize for keeping you wait.
不好意思 倒让您久等了
We're all colleagues from Peking University.
都是北大的同人
Based on seniority, I'm taking my seat at the head of the table.
论资排辈 我坐主席
Dean Chen should take the second seat after that,
陈学长次之
followed by Director Li.
李主任再次之
According to the etiquette of Qing Empire,
按照大清国的规矩
Dr. Hu wouldn't even be eligible for seats at the table.
胡博士入席还不够资格
But today,
但是今天
since you were sent here by Chancellor Cai,
你是蔡元培校长派遣来的
please take the end seat.
那就请末席入座吧
Thank you for offering us the seats.
谢赐座
Thank you, Professor Gu, for offering us the seats.
谢辜教授赐座
Okay, let's sit down.
好 坐吧
Waiter,
伙计
you may now bring the warm dishes.
可以起热菜了
Coming soon!
得
Boundless universe, bright sun and moon.
大千世界 朗朗乾坤
There are only two decent men in China at the moment.
眼下中国只有两个好人
One is Mr. Cai Yuanpei.
一个是蔡元培先生
The other is me, Gu Hongming.
一个就是我辜鸿铭
For after Mr. Cai was selected to be a member of Imperial Academy,
因为蔡公点了翰林以后
he refused to become an official, but rather joined the revolution.
不肯做官 而是去革命
He's still part the revolution even till now.
直到现在还在革命
As for me, after I followed Master Zhang Zhidong (one of the four most famous officials of the late Qing dynasty, known for advocating controlled reform and modernization of Chinese troops)
我呢 自从跟了香师张之洞
I served the Qing Court,
做了前清的官员
and I have remained a Royalist till today.
一直到现在还在保皇
For a Royalist such as myself,
我这个保皇党啊
I only follow orders of two people.
只听两个人的使唤
One is the Emperor himself,
一个是皇上
the other is Mr. Cai Yuanpei.
另一个 就是蔡元培先生
Mr. Cai is my chancellor.
蔡公是我的校长
He invited me to this meal today, so I was obliged to come.
今天让我来吃饭我不能不来呀
Therefore, this first cup
所以呢 我这第一杯
is to Chancellor Cai.
敬的是蔡校长
We can get started.
开始吧
Please.
来
In terms of gourmet food,
要说这美食啊
the top restaurants in Beijing are the "Eight Inns".
北京城首推的就是八大楼
Among the "Eight Inns",
这八大楼里呢
Dongxing Inn takes the first place.
这东兴楼拔头份
Of course.
那是
The dishes they prepare here belong to the Jiaodong Cuisine of Shandong Province.
东兴楼属于山东的胶东菜系
You'll be able to have their signature dishes in a bit.
等一会儿你会吃到他们的名菜
Braised Sliced Chicken with Egg and Milk
芙蓉鸡片
Stewed Cuttlefish Roe
烩乌鱼蛋
Braised Sea Cucumber with Scallion
葱烧海参
Stir-fried Chicken with Soybean Sauce
酱爆鸡丁
Deep-fried Chicken Gizzards, and etc.
炸鸭胗 等等等等
Dr. Hu, this is your first time here, right?
胡博士第一次来吧
Do the dishes sound intriguing to you?
听着新鲜
This meal with Professor Gu is
今天跟辜教授在一起
really eye-opening to me.
我真是开了眼哪
Professor Gu,
辜教授
may I propose a toast to you?
我可以敬您一杯吗
Hang on a minute,
等等
I thought you are here to seek me as your master.
你不是要拜我为师吗
I have to quiz you first.
我得先考考你的学问
Please ask away, sir.
请先生指教
Last year when Zhang Xun was having his birthday,
去年张勋过生日的时候
I sent him a couplet.
我送了他一副对子
The first line was "Lotus wilts and the rain-holding top gone"
这上联是荷尽已无擎雨盖
The second line reads "Chrysanthemum withers but the frost-resistant stem remains"
这下联呢是菊残犹有傲霜枝
What are these two lines referring to?
这是什么意思啊
In the line "Chrysanthemum withers but the frost-resistant stem remains"
这菊残犹有傲霜枝
the "frost-resistant stem" naturally refers to
傲霜枝自然指的就是
the queue you and Zhang Xun both keeps.
张勋和您老先生头上的子
The "rain-holding top" Professor Gu just mentioned
刚才辜教授所说的擎雨盖
is of course...
那自然说的就是
what is it?
是什么呢
I actually have no idea, Professor Gu.
我 我还真不知道 辜教授
Director Li,
李主任啊
you're the director of Peking University Library.
你是北大图书馆的主任
You should know what it is.
这个你应该知道吧
Professor Gu, I have little talent,
辜教授 大钊不才
but if I'm not mistaken,
要是大钊没有猜错的话
this "rain-holding top" should be
这个擎雨盖应该就是
the hat worn by Qing Officials.
清朝官员头上的 帽子
Smart! You're deserving the title of library director.
聪明 不愧是图书馆的李主任
Dr. Hu, now you're learning, right?
胡博士 开了眼了吧
Thank you for your teaching.
受教
I'm talentless, I'll drink this as a punishment.
胡适不才 我自罚一杯
Dean Chen has always been articulate person with eloquent speech,
陈学长历来是快人快语呀
how come you're so quiet today?
今天怎么一言不发了
Professor Gu,
辜教授
upon hearing Professor Gu's informed opinion,
刚才听辜教授一番宏论
I all of a sudden
就突然觉得
feels... slightly nervous
就觉得 有点紧张了
and didn't know what to contribute to the conversation.
就不知道怎么说了
I'm just afraid...
这个就怕
Dean Chen is the standard-bearer of New Culture,
陈学长是新文化的旗手
while I'm the clear stream among the Royalists.
我呢是保皇派的清流
We're vehicles on two parallel tracks,
你我是两股道上跑的车
and will never have any intersections.
永远也没有交叉点
But Dean Chen is paying respect to worthy and virtuous men today
不过今天陈学长礼贤下士
through this
摆了这么一桌
sumptuous banquet.
丰盛的酒席来招待我
You must have some favor to ask me.
一定是有事有求于我吧
Now that we've had three rounds of wine,
现在既然是酒过三巡
please just tell me what it is, Dean Chen.
请陈学长直言吧
Well, I'll drink up this to show my respect to you first.
那好 我先干为敬啊
Professor Gu,
辜教授
I assume you've already heard of
想必您也已经知道了
the dismissal of Cartwright from our university.
本校解聘英籍教授克德莱一事
Of course, I have.
当然知道
If it was not for Mr Cai's mercy,
如果要不是蔡先生发慈悲
you probably would have
恐怕你早就会把我
categorized me with people like Cartwright.
划到克德莱一类去吧
Professor Gu's matter has reached forgone conclusion.
辜教授的事情早已有了定论
But the discharge of Cartwright
现如今裁撤克德莱
had become a thorny pending case nowadays.
倒成了一桩令人棘手的悬案
Cartwright instigated the British Prime Minister,
克德莱动用英国首相
the British Embassy and various of other power
和驻华使馆等多种力量
to pressure Peking University into their terms.
来给我北大施压
They are pressing false charges against us, including breach of contract
巫陷我北大违法 毁约
and discrimination against foreigners.
歧视外人
They are demanding apologies, financial compensation and resumption of posts.
要求道 赔款 复职
They will be satisfied with nothing but Mr Cai's destruction.
欲置我蔡公于死地而后快
This is outrageous!
岂有此理
This Cartwright,
这个克德莱
how dare he coerce our Mr. Cai!
公然竟敢害我蔡公
I, Gu Hongming, will fight him to death!
我辜鸿铭一定跟他血战到底
After a lot of twists and turns,
几经周折
Beiyang Government finally agreed that
现在北洋政府终于同意了
Peking University can form a professor delegation
我们北大成立教授团
to formally negotiate with the British Embassy
与英国驻华使馆通过谈判
regarding the discharge of Cartwright.
来协商克德莱的解聘案
Mr. Cai pointed out,
蔡先生就说了
how can we go to court with the British
说你跟英国人打官司
without Gu Tangsheng, the Britain Expert?
你能缺了汤生这个英国通吗
Indeed.
是啊
This why today the three of us
所以今天我等三人
entrusted by Mr. Cai and on behalf of Peking University
是受蔡先生之委托
to invite you to take up this important duty.
代表北大来请辜教授出山的
We sincerely hope Professor Gu would condescend to
悬请辜教授能够屈尊
join our professor delegation
参加我们的教授团
and fight it out with the Brits!
与那英国人一决高下
No one knows me better than Mr. Cai!
知我者蔡公也啊
You don't have to do it yourself, I'll help.
您别动 我来
I'll help, don't worry.
我来 您别动
Sorry, sorry.
不好意思 不好意思
I was just... Alright.
我只是 好
Thank you, thank you!
谢谢 谢谢
Great, Dean Chen,
好陈学长
Director Li,
李主任
Dr. Hu,
胡博士
for this professor delegation, I'm in!
这个教授团我参加了
Let's all drink a toast for this!
就为这个 咱们于上一杯
Wonderful!
好
I, old Gu,
我老辜啊
went to Britain at the age of ten.
十岁就去了英国
I studied in Europe at fourteen.
十四岁留学欧洲
I'm very familiar with the mindset of westerners (British people)
我对洋人的这个脑子
as well as their dispositions and manners.
他们的秉性习惯我非常熟悉
We can tell.
那是
Let me give you a few pointers:
我给你们先讲几条
First,
第一
aloof and cunning.
冷漠滑头
They're scared of taking responsibilities,
特别害怕承担责任
they shirk as much as they can.
而且是能逃避就逃避
Right on point!
可不是
Second,
第二
hypocritical and vain.
虚伪虚荣
On the one hand, they're greedy for profits,
很看重利益
on the other hand, they often feel ashamed to ask bluntly.
但是又羞于启齿
Exactly!
可不是嘛
They care only for the show.
爱做表面文章
Third,
第三呢
exclusiveness,
排他
Yes!
对
unsociable, arrogant, stubborn and inarticulate,
孤傲固执
Indeed!
还真是
difficult towards foreigners.
很不容易与外族人交融
Typically island country mindset.
典型的岛国心理
You're right!
没错
Forth,
第四呢
Conservativeness
保守
Yes!
对
(Translating "conservativeness" into Chinese)
就是保守
Extremely reluctant to accept new things.
特别不容易接受新生事物
I'll handle this case successfully.
这件事情你就交给我了
As soon as I show up,
只要吾一出马
they will be intimidated.
彼必定害怕
As soon as I speak,
吾一开口
they will flee pell-mell.
彼必定望风而逃
Awesome!
好
Professor Gu,
辜教授
Mr. Cai also asked me to tell me that
蔡先生他也让我告诉您
the chief negotiator of our delegation is
就我们这个教授团的首席谈判官
Hu Shi.
是胡适
The others are supposed to support his work.
其他人主要是配合
So this is
蔡先生
Mr. Cai's arrangement?
是这么安排的呀
Indeed.
可不是嘛
“Within plane tree blossoms lining the roads on Mount Danshan,”
桐花万里丹山路
“Sweeter is the singing of young phoenixes than that of seniors.”
凤清于老凤声
Alright, then, I, Gu Hongming, will submit myself to the service of
那我辜鸿铭就舍了这张老脸
this vernacular kid, as his military advisor.
给你这个白话娃娃当一回军师吧
Great!
好来
Professor Gu,
辜教授
The three of us will propose a toast to you together.
那我们三位共同敬您一杯
Thank you, Sir.
谢先生
Good!
好
For Peking University,
为了北大
and for Mr. Cai, cheers!
为了蔡公 干杯
Cheers!
干杯
The Chinese guests will soon arrive.
中国客人一会儿就到
Is everything ready?
一切都准备好了吗
Yes, everything is ready.
是的 都准备好了
Jordan!
朱尔典
The people that are coming today,
今天来的这几位
are top talents from Peking University.
可都是北京大学的新锐
All of them are good at debate.
个个能说会道
So be careful.
您可千方注意
Don't be fooled by them.
不要被他们绕了进去
Don't worry, Cartwright.
放心吧 克德莱
Peking University has sent
北京大学今天派出了
a strange negotiating team today.
一个奇怪的谈判阵容
The leading figures from the old and the new culture
新旧两派的领军人物
will be present in the meeting.
都到了我英国使馆
This will be our honour.
这倒也是我们的荣幸
to give them an opportunity
能在这里给他们
to hold a cultural debate here.
开一个文化辩论会
Are you referring to Hong Ming?
您是说鸿铭吗
Exactly.
正是
From what I know,
据我所知
Hong Ming is
鸿铭可是
Chen Duxiu and Hu Shi's sworn enemy.
陈独秀和胡适的死对头
So you're saying,
您的意思是
you will make them quarrel here?
让他们在这几吵起来
If it happens,
果真如此的话
tt would be a good show for us.
那岂不是一场好戏 不是吗
Indeed.
是的
Today you are the main speaker.
今天您是主谈
At the debate later
一会谈判
You will be the first speaker
由您第一个发言
Don't worry, I know
没有问题 知道
Let us prepare first
您先准备一下
Gentlemen, please have a seat
各位先生请坐吧
Let me introduce you to
我来介绍一下
This is the diplomat from the British Embassy,
这位是英国驻华使馆公使
Mr Jordan
朱尔典先生
This is the first secretary from the embassy
这位是公使馆一等秘书
Mr Charles
查尔顿先生
And I am sure you all must know
这位大家都认识
Mr Cartwright
克德莱先生
You should address me as Professor Cartwright
您应该称呼我为克德莱教授
This is the dean of Liberal Arts of Peking University
这位是北京大学文科学长
Professor Chen Du Xiu
陈独秀教授
This is Professor Hu She
这是胡适教授
This is
这位是
Professor Gu
辜教授
I welcome you here
欢迎您前排就座
This is Mr Li Da Zhao
这位是李大钊先生
One behalf of the British Embassy
我代表英国公使馆
I welcome all Peking University professors
欢迎北京大学的各位教授
especially Professor Gu Hong Ming
特别是辜鸿铭教授
who is highly respected by us westerners
是我们西方人十分尊敬的大学者
It is a great honour and pleasure
能和辜先生在一个房间里谈判
To be able to negotiate with Professor Gu personally
是一件十分荣幸和愉快的事情
Let's get started
我们开始吧
Who is going to talk first
谁先谈
Professor Hu She is Peking University's main speaker
胡适教授是北大教授团的主谈
Let Professor Hu She begin
请胡适教授先说
Good morning, gentlemen
各位先生早上好
I'm really astonished by the note of protest
接到外交部转来的英国驻华使馆
against wrongful and unfair dismissal
关于抗议北京大学
of Professor Cartwright from his position
无故解聘克德莱教授的照会后
at Peking University
北京大学
Things like dismissal of the foreign teachers from Peking University
与外籍教员解除聘任关系
are common situations
是学校在教学管理中
in education management
经常发生的一种普遍现象
According to students' complaints,
根据学生的举报
Peking University has carried out a thorough investigation
北京大学对克德莱先生的
of Professor Cartwright's teaching level,
教学水平 教学态度
attitudes
教学行为等方面
behaviour and other aspects.
进行了深入细致的调查
The investigation has revealed
调查结果显示
As a result, large amount of evidence indicated that
大量确酱的证据表明
Professor Cartwright
克德莱先生
Is not competent at his job at all
不仅完全不能胜任教学工作
Furthermore
更甚的是
He violated university rules
还存在严重违反校规校纪等问题
which brought negative impact
给北大的教学造成了许多
and irretrievable loss
无法挽回的损失
Therefore, based on relevant regulation
鉴于此 校评议委员会
and rules made by the government and the university
依据国家和学校制定的相关条例
the review committee decided to discharge Mr Cartwright from his position
解除了克德莱的聘任合同
This is our internal affair
这完全是北京大学的内部事务
It has nothing to do with
与英国政府
The British Government or the British embassy
英国驻华使馆没有半点的关系
Professor Hu
胡教授
You sound like you are not here to negotiate
听您的口气不像是来商议事情
But to denouce us
而是来兴师问罪的
Professor Cartwright is a British citizen
克德莱教授是英国公民
He was introduced by the British embassy
他是经英国使馆
to the Chinese education ministry
介绍给中国教育部
to teach at Peking University
去北大任教的
Now, his interests in China have been damaged
现在他的利益在中国受到了损失
Certainly, the British Embassy cannot ignore it
因此 英国使馆不能置之不理
Moreover,
此外
It is a sacred and undeniable right to protest
这也是神圣不可侵犯的权利
Professor Cartwright's losses
克德莱先生利益上的损失
are caused by his own actions
完全是他自己造成的
It is the consequence of his actions
是由自取
May I ask Mr Diplomat,
请问公使先生
If a British person
如果一个英国人
Has committed a crime overseas
在非治外法权地犯了法
Has murdered somebody,
杀了人
And when the local government seeks to use the law
当地政府要依法
to punish him,
追究他的刑事责任
will the British Embassy raise an issue?
英国使馆也要提出抗议吗
You are playing with the words
这是在偷换概念
The British Embassy has stated very clearly in the note
英国使馆在照会中写得清清楚楚
That Professor Cartwright's teaching contract
克德莱的任教合同
is issued by the Chinese ministry of education
是贵国教育部签发的
Peking University has no right to dismiss him
北京大学根本无权解聘
In addition, Professor Cartwright's teaching period is 4 years
还有 克德莱的任教期是四年
The contract states that
合同条款规定
There should be no early termination without good reason
不得无故提前解聘
Now, Peking University has unilaterally
现在 北京大学单方面
dismissed a British citizen
解聘英籍教授
which not only usurps power,
这既越权又违规
So it is reasonable if we
所以我们是合理的
take action
我们应该采取行动
and protect the rights of our citizens
保护我们公民的权利
Mr Minister
公使先生
I'm afraid that you have no rights
恐怕关于这个问题
to interfere in this issue
你们还真的是无权干涉
Peking University's actions
因为北京大学的做法
are completely legal
完全是合法的
We have brought several documents
我们带来了几份文件
These documents from the Chinese education ministry
这是中国教育部
and Peking University regulations
和北京大学颁布的条令 条例
Are sufficient to prove that
足以证明
Professor Cartwright's dismissal is legal
解聘克德莱先生是合法的
In addition, some of these documents
另外还有一些文件
prove that
里边说明了
Professor Cartwright is completely incapable of
克德莱先生根本无法胜任
teaching at Peking University
北京大学的教学工作
He has also sevrely broken
而且严重违反了
Peking University's rules
北京大学的校规和校纪
All these prove that
这些也足以说明
Professor Cartwright's dismissal is logical
解聘克德莱先生是合理的
Some might even say his dismissal is necessary
甚至是必须的
So,
因此 现在
I will now hand these documents to you
我把这些材料给您过目
Please think about it
请慎重考虑
Professor Gu
辜教授
I have once spent 2 silver dollars
我曾经花两块大洋买了张门票
to be able to buy a seat at your lecture
去听您的讲座
I have also remembered clearly what you have said
我记得您曾经说过
about the biggest difference between the Chinese and Europeans
中国人与欧洲人最大的区别
was that the Chinese do things like children
是中国人始终像小孩子一样
According to how they feel in their hearts
靠心灵的感觉做事情
While Europeans are more like adults
欧洲人更像成人
Relying on mature thinking
靠成熟的头脑去思考事情
You are so right
您说得太对了
The documents that you have provided us
您看你们的这些文件
are totally random
太随意了
This is a document signed by Li Yuan Hong
这一份是黎元洪签署的
This one signed by Hu Ren Yuan
这一份是胡仁源
This is by Fan Yuan Lian
这一份是范源廉的
And this
这一份
actually writted by Cai Yuan Pei
又是蔡元培自己制定的
Your whole country
你们这个国家
can change leaders at will, at every level
可以随意更换各级领导人
just like a kid playing games
像小孩子玩游戏
Every new leader
每一个新上台的人
has a new set of rules
都要制定一套规矩
Since you have provided so many documents
现在你拿出这么多的文件
who do you want me to listen to?
你让我听谁的
Mr Diplomat
公使先生
it seems like you have wasted your money
看来你这两块大洋的听课费
listening to my lecture
算是白花了
Clearly, you have misunderstood my teachings
我的讲座你根本就没有听懂啊
I would like to remind you once again
我还要再提醒你一点
your arrogance, bias and rudeness
您身上的那种傲慢 偏见与无礼
are very rarely seen in the Chinese
在我们中国人身上是很少发现的
Professor Gu
辜教授
I'm not here to listen to a lecture
今天我不是来听您讲课的
The United Kingdom is a country that respects human rights
英国是一个尊重人权
and abides by contracts
遵守契约的国家
In British Universities
在英国的大学里
there wouldn't be such violations
绝不会发生这种违反契药
Prematurely terminating a foreign teacher
提前裁撤外籍教员的事情
Mr Diplomat,
公使先生
it seems like you have spent too much time in China
看来你是在中国待的时间太长了
You have forgotten your own history
把你们自己的历史都忘记了
Let me give you a lesson
来我现在再给你补习一下
In 1886,
一八八六年
The University of Edinburgh once fired
爱丁堡大学曾经开除了两名
2 professors who made a scene while drunk
因为酶酒闹事的教授
In 1889,
一八八九年
the University of Oxford once fired 10 foreign professors
牛津大学裁撤了十多名外籍教授
of which 8 of them had not completed their tenure
其中有八名还是没有到期的教授
In 1902,
一九〇二年
The University of Cambridge once fired
剑桥大学曾经开除了
an American professor
一位美国教授
and a Japanese Professor
和一位日本的讲师
In fact, this year due to the war,
就在去年 因为战争的原医
Britian, France
英国 法国
and a few other countries
还有一些国家
immediately fired all professors
一下子解聘了全部的德国
and students from Germany and Austria-Hungary
和奥帝国的学者及教授
I would like to ask you, Mr Diplomat
我想问一下公使先生
If you can do so,
既然你们可以这样做
Why can't we?
我们为什么就不能呢
Is this your highly regarded
这就是你们奉为神灵的
values of human rights, freedom and equality?
民主 自由 平等吗
Professor Gu,
辜教授
Thank you for bringing up the war
感谢您提到了战争
I would like to remind eveyrone seated here
我要提醒在座诸位
that Britian and China are now working togther
英国和中国现在正在协同作战
Your actions have
你们的这种做法
affected the cooperation between the 2 countries
已经影响了两国的合作
Have you thought about the consequences?
你们想过后果吗
Can you afford to bear this responsibility
你们负得起这个责任吗
Mr Minister,
公使先生
are you threatening us?
你是在威胁我们吗
I am trying to get you to face the reality
我是要你们正视现实
that this matter has already attracted the
这件事已经引起了
attention of the British Prime Minister
英国首相的关注
and also attracted the attention of The Chinese President and Premier
贵国总统和总理也在高度关注中
You are so obstinate
你们如此一意孤行
Does Cai Yuan Pei still want to be
蔡元培还想不想
the president of Peking University?
做这个北大的校长了
If we can go against our conscience,
我们如果可以放弃原则
and crumble under pressure
屈从权势
We would not be here to debate
那今天我们就不来谈判了
I think we can end this negotiation
我看这个谈判可以结束了
Mr Diplomat
公使先生
Here you are
这个给你
Take good care of it
好好保管
Goodbye, gentlemen
再见 先生们
Cartwright,
克德莱
I cannot do anything about it
我已经无能为力了
Handle it yourself
你自行其便吧
I'll take them to court
我要把他们告上法庭
I want to let you know
我跟你说一下
Chen Du Xiu is back
陈独秀他们回来了
From what we know
初战告捷
it seems that Jordan doesn't care anymore
现在朱尔典不管了
he wants to let Cartwright do whatever he wants
他让克德莱呀自行其便了
This matter is not so simple
没那么简单
Jordan has called Duan Qi Rui
朱尔典给段祺瑞打电话了
He still hopes the country honours the contract,
还是以协约国为要扶
and hopes the government can interfere
希望政府出面干涉
Duan Qi Rui has called me
段祺瑞给我打来电话
and suggested that we solve it amicably
提出最好协商解决
to avoid the courts if possible
尽量不要上法庭
We are not the ones who wants to go to court
不是我们要上法庭
It is Cartwright who desires it
是克德莱要打官司
We can't possibly ignore it
你说 我们能不奉陪吗
We should definitely prepare for a lawsuit
官司当然要准备打
I have already found 2 lawyers
我已经给你请好了两个辩护人
There are Peking University professors
都是你们北大的教授
One is Wang Chong Hui
一个是王宠惠
The other is Zhang Yao Zeng
一个是张耀曾
They should be sufficient
够级别吧
That's great
好啊 好啊 好啊
There were both previous ministers of law
他们都是前司法总长
With the 2 of them,
有这两位出山哪
we will definitely win
那胜券在握呀
Going to court will be the last resort
上法庭是后话
I have discussed with Fu Zeng Xiang
我和傅增湘商量过了
It is of utmost importance
当务之急
We will need to take down Cartwright's ego
是要把克德莱的器张气焰压下去
to let him know the consequences
让他自知理号
that if he continues to make a scene
知道再闹下去
he will be left with nothing
只能是身败名裂
What do you think?
你看这样好不好
Expose all of Cartwright's wrongdoings
把克德莱那些烂事给他抖接出去
He will know who is stronger
他就知道那些厉害了
Yes, make good use of the 2 cards up your sleeve
对用好你手上的两张牌
Cartwright, what is going on
克德莱 这是怎么回事
Public opinion is overwhelming against the UK
铺天盖地的典论都在指责英国
You've caused the government lots of trouble
你给英国政府惹了大麻烦
Many British people in China have lost face
你让英国人在中国丢尽了脸
How do you want this to end?
你要我们怎么收场
Jordan, we must not give in
朱尔典 我们不能退让
We cannot lose to the Chinese
我们不能输给中国人
Call Duan Qi Rui
你给段祺瑞打电话
Put pressure on him
你要向他施加压力
Let him replace Cai Yuan Pei
你让他撤换蔡元培
Cartwright
克德莱
You're crazy
你疯了
Wang Da Man isn't even returning my calls
汪大蔓都不回我的电话了
Much less Duan Qi Rui
更不要说段祺瑞了
Who do you think you are
你以为你是谁
Do you think you can reverse this whole situation?
你以为你能扭转乾坤吗
I'll take them to court then
那我就跟他们上法庭
Do you think you can win?
你以为上法庭能赢吗
You will only lose even worse
只能输得更惨
Do you know who their lawyers are?
你知道他们的辩护人都有谁吗
One of them is Wang Chong Hui
一个是王宠惠
An expert in English and American law
英美法系的专家
The other is Zhang Yao Zeng
另一个是张耀曾
An expert in civil law
大陆法系的专家
They are both universally recognized as legal experts
这二位都是举世公认的法学大师
and have served as chief justice of the Republic of China
都当过中华民国的司法总长
Fight against them
你跟他们斗
and you will end up discredited and compromised
只能是自取其唇
What should I do then?
那么 我该怎么办
You must help me find a solution
你要帮我找到解决办法
[?] Cartwright,
屈服吧 克德莱
the Chinese have determined to fight us.
中国人现在是铁了心要跟我们斗
And we only suffer
再顽抗下去
greater losses if we persist in this.
我们只会受到更大的损失
Britain is now at war,
现在英国正在打仗
and I don't want to create more problems because of this matter.
不希望因为你这件事情节外生枝
Duan Qirui and Feng Guozhang
段祺瑞和冯国璋
are fighting each other about affairs of the southern government.
正在为南方政府的事情斗法
We can't allow our affairs
不可能因为我们的事情
to offend Cai Yuanpei and the students.
去得罪蔡元培和学生
No way.
没办法
We have to give up, Cartwright.
我们必须退让 克德莱
How?
怎么
How to give up?
怎么个退让法
Tomorrow, I will meet with Wang Daxie,
明天我约见汪大愛
and ask him to mediate
请他从中翰旋
and give us a way out.
给个台阶
Listening to Beethoven's "Symphony of Heroes".
听上贝多芬的《英雄交响曲》了
Probably something good is going on.
大概是有什么好事吧
I was waiting for you.
正等着你呢
Good.
好
Come, come. Please sit.
来来来 请坐
Tell me, what's the good news?
你说说 有什么喜事
Early this morning,
今天一早啊
Jordan made an urgent appointment with me
朱尔典就紧急约见我
regarding the Cartwright matter,
面谈克德莱的事情
saying that there were new instructions from the British government.
说是英国政府有了新的指示
I was waiting
我呀 渗着他
until noon just to see him.
拖到中午才见他
Right, waiting that long.
对渗得对
As soon as we met, Jordan told me
朱尔典一见面就跟我说
that Prime Minister Lloyd George considered
劳合·乔治首相考虑到
China and the United Kingdom as allies.
中国和英国的协约国的关系
He decided to downplay
决定从大局着眼
Cartwright's dismissal from the overall situation,
淡化克德莱解聘的事情
respect the ruling of Peking University
尊重北大的裁决
and let Cartwright come home as soon as possible.
让克德莱尽快回国
Does Lloyd George have the luxury
劳合·乔治他有这个闲心
to take care of this matter?
管这个事吗
It's just an excuse.
托词而已
Is it?
就是
Jordan said
朱尔典说啊
they have persuaded Cartwright to drop the lawsuit
他们已经劝说克德莱撤诉
and stop getting entangled with Peking University.
不再与北大纠缠
I hope Peking University will compromise
希望北大也做一个让步
and give Cartwright a way out.
给克德莱一个台阶
What kind of way out does he want?
他要什么台阶
Jordan said that he hoped that Peking University
朱尔典说 他希望北大
would stop spreading the Cartwright affair
不要再向中外媒介
to Chinese and foreign media.
扩散克德莱的事情
At the same time, he hoped
同时呢希望在经济上
that Cartwright would be financially compensated.
能够给克德莱做适当的补偿
This Jordan is very cunning.
这个朱尔典胶猎得很哪
If we pay the financial compensation,
我们要是给了经济补偿
doesn't that mean we admit that we are at fault?
不就承认我们有错了吗
We can't agree to this.
这条我们不能答应
Let me finish what I have to say.
你听我把话说完
This afternoon, the Prime Minister's Office called me
今天下午 总理府分别给我
and Fu Zengxiang separately
和傅增湘打了电话
to convey Duan Qirui's instructions
传达段祺瑞的指示
that the British should not ask for too much, should cooperate
英国人要求不高 应积极配合
and not cause any trouble.
切勿节外生枝
This old Duan.
这个老段哪
He's afraid of the British.
他是怕英国人
I and Fu Zengxiang worked together.
我和傅增湘合计了
The result has exceeded our expectation.
这个结果已经超出了我们的预想
As for the financial compensation,
至于经济补偿 可以变通
it can be resolved by the Ministry of Education.
由教育部来解决
The reason is that Cartwright signed his contract
理由是克德莱他的签约
with the Ministry of Education.
就是跟教育部签的
Do you think it's fine?
你看行不行啊
I think so.
我觉得可以
Can we make him an offer?
我们能不能给他提个条件
Tell me.
你说说看
Let Cartwright come to Peking University
让克德莱到北大来
in front of all the teachers and students
当着北大的全校师生的面
to sign the letter of termination.
在解聘书上签字 以正视听
I think that's feasible.
我看可行
Jordan said that both sides should give him a way out,
他朱尔典说双方都要给个台阶
and I will give him a note early tomorrow morning.
明天一早我就照会他
Good.
好
Brother Botang.
伯棠兄
Then I'll go back and wait for your good news.
那我回去等您的好消息喽
Good.
好
Yucai, this building looks old.
豫才 这建筑看上去有些年头了
This Shaoxing Guildhall
这绍兴会馆
was built in the sixth year of the Daoguang Emperor's reign (1826).
建于道光六年
It was formerly known as Shanyin Huiji Liangyi Guildhall,
原名山阴会稽两邑会馆
is mainly used to entertain Juren (imperial bureaucratic rank) from Shanyin and Huiji counties
主要是招待山阴和会稽两县
who are going to Beijing to take the exam.
进京赶考的举人
It has been nearly a hundred years, right?
算起来也近一百年了吧
[Zhou Shuren (Lu Xun), styled Yucai, Civil servant under the Ministry of Education]
历经沧桑呀
Even the ancients inscriptions are older than this house.
比这房子更沧桑的是这些古碑文
It's reminiscent of ancient times.
让人发思古之情啊
Studying Buddhist scriptures and copying ancient tablets
钻研佛经 抄写古碑
is Yucai's daily habit now.
是豫才现在的常态呀
I heard that
我听说这屋子
there was a woman who hanged herself in this house.
好像还吊死过一个女人
No, that was outside that door.
没有 那是那门外
So no one dares to live in this house,
所以 这屋子没人敢住
except my brother.
只有我兄长敢
Brother Yucai, aren't you depressed when you live here?
那豫才兄 你住在这几不压抑吗
Depressed,
压抑的
I'm not the only one who's depressed in this tree-mending (=Bushu) bookstore.
又岂止我这一间补树书屋呢
Outside the bookstore,
书屋之外
the rancid air was unbearable.
那些腐臭之息更是不堪
I saw the Xinhai Revolution in those years.
这些年 我见了辛亥革命
Then the Second Revolution.
见过了二次革命
Then Yuan Shikai's self-proclaimation as Emperor and the Zhang Xun Restoration.
见过袁世凯称帝张勋复辟
It seems that this society is rotten.
看来看去就觉得这社会啊烂透了
With no cure at all.
根本无药可救
Brother Yucai, I thought
豫才兄 小弟以为
that since Heaven created Man,
上天既然创造了人
it should give them a way out.
就应该给他们一条活路
There is still a cure.
药还是有的
Only someone needs to find it.
只不过需要有人去找才行
Where's the cure?
药在何处
Who is the person looking for the cure?
寻药之人又是谁
Me.
我
Us.
我们
This cure is your masterpiece, Brother Yucai.
这药呢就是豫才兄你的大作呀
"New Youth",
《新青年》
I've read it.
我看了
Lukewarm water is not enough.
温瞰水 不够劲
Please ask Brother Yucai to enlighten me.
请豫才兄赐教
First, you advocate vernacular,
其—你们倡导白话文
but I write in classical Chinese and semi-classical Chinese.
自己却用文言文和半文言文写作
"Holding a pipa that half hides the face." (Verse from "Pipa xing" (816))
犹抱琵琶半遮面
Second, to advocate and popularize vernacular
其二 提倡和普及白话文
is to have works that are popular with the public.
根本是要有大众喜闻乐见的作品
I think
我以为
writing novels in vernacular
用白话文写小说
is the best way to popularize vernacular,
是普及白话文最好的形式
but you just don't have any works in this form.
而恰恰你们没有这方面的作品
Third, and most importantly,
其三 也是最重要的
you keep saying that you want to declare war against the Three Fundamental Bonds of Confucianism.
你们口口声声要讨伐孔教三纲
But it's all about great principles,
但讲的全是些大道理
and most people's understanding is not profound.
认识也不深刻
It's impossible to touch people's souls
没有形象思维的作品
without thinking in images.
是根本不可能触及到人们的灵魂
Yucai,
豫才
I've learnt so much,
受教
what you just said has been enlightening,
刚刚一番话 入木三分
and gets to the heart of "New Youth".
句句切中《新青年》 的要害
Sir,
先生
now that we have our doctor,
既然已经查明了病医
please perform your operation.
那就赶紧动手术吧
Stop sitting on the sidelines.
莫再作壁上观了
No more "holding a pipa that half hides the face".
莫再犹抱琵琶半遮面了
Be bold and resolute, Yucai.
大刀阔斧吧豫才
I will try.
我试试
Great!
好
Just waiting for you to say this.
就等你这句话呢
Yucai, as long as you strike hard,
豫才 你只要一出手
you will definitely become a banner.
绝对是一面旗帜
Brother Yucai,
豫才兄
I regret that we didn't meet sooner.
相见恨晚
Yucai,
豫才
the trip was well worthwhile. I'm glad to hear the good news.
不虚此行 静候佳音
Then let's go now.
那我们走了
I am waiting for your cure.
我等你的药哦
Like the autumn wind sweeping the fallen leaves.
秋风扫落叶嘛这是
I've already heard of this once before.
我倒是已经领教过一次了
But it can also be seen that this person
但是也由此可见这个人
has great charm.
极具人格魅力
He's able to recruit people with high ideals to do things for them in the future.
将来定能招揽有志之士为其做事
Deqian doesn't say much.
德潜不多说
I also like that Shouchang.
那个守常我也很喜欢
He acts steady and modest.
为人稳重 谦和
I believe he can do great things in the future.
我相信将来他一定也能做大事
Oh right, several old classmates,
对了 昔白南京水师学堂
such as Ren Guangming of Nanjing Navy Academy, came to Beijing to meet you.
任广明等几个老同学来京公于
They wanted to catch up with you.
他们都想能见上你一面 叙叙旧
Are they here for the Ministry of Education?
他们是来教育部办事的吗
Why don't they come to me directly?
为什么不来直接找我呢
Everyone knows you are in a bad mood.
人家都知道你心情不好
They don't dare disturb you.
不敢贸然打扰你
It's a pleasure
哪里的话
to have friends from afar.
有朋自远方来 不亦乐乎
Please arrange it. I'll ask them to rinse the pot.
你安排一下 我请他们涮锅子
Alright.
好
Sir,
先生
do you think I understand this part correctly?
您看这部分我理解得对不对
Let me see.
我看看啊
This part
这一部分啊
is right in general.
大体意思是对的
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
Very well.
好
Hello, sir.
先生 您好
Excuse me.
打扰您
Hello.
您好
Excuse me, where is Professor Hu Shizhi's office?
请问胡适之老师的办公室在哪儿
Hu Shizhi?
胡适之啊
You see that, open the door.
你看到那个敬开门
There are some ladies laughing in that room.
里边有女士笑声的 就那间
Thank you.
谢谢
Doctor Hu,
胡博士
how do you write vernacular poems
你说白话诗到底该怎么写
to make them catchy?
才更能朗朗上口呢
She asked this question well.
她这个问题问得好啊
Mr. Huang Zunxian said that
黄遵宪先生说
I wrote my mouth with my own handwriting.
我以我手写我口
Thank you.
谢谢
What does that mean?
什么意思呢
Actually, the reason is very simple.
其实道理很简单
Without emotion,
没有情感
without thought, vernacular poetry
没有思想的白话诗
is like a poem without mind.
它就像没有头脑
Who can not love beauty
没有情感的美人一样
in this world
在这个世界上
like a beauty without emotion?
谁能不爱美人呢
Who would love a zombie
谁会去爱没有情感
without emotion or mind?
没有头脑的優户呢
Brother Mengzou.
孟邹兄
Come in!
快进来
Sorry, everyone.
抱歉了各位
there is a guest here.
家里来了客人
Let's talk next time.
我们下一次再聊吧
How can this be over before it's fun?
这还没尽兴 怎么就结束了
Awfully sorry.
非常抱歉
Professor Hu.
胡教授
Can I have a Western-style farewell with you?
能不能和你来一次西式的告别
Of course.
当然
Goodbye, Doctor Hu.
博士再见
Thank you.
谢谢